<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse and true recitall of euerie particular of the victorie obtained by the French king, on Wednesday the fourth of March, being Ashwednesday Also of his good successe that he hath had since that time, in taking of certaine townes. Out of French into English. Seene and allowed.</title>
            <title>Discours veritable de la victoire obtenue par le roy en la batialle donnee pres le village d'Evry. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119814</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855020</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20490</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20490)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 569:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse and true recitall of euerie particular of the victorie obtained by the French king, on Wednesday the fourth of March, being Ashwednesday Also of his good successe that he hath had since that time, in taking of certaine townes. Out of French into English. Seene and allowed.</title>
                  <title>Discours veritable de la victoire obtenue par le roy en la batialle donnee pres le village d'Evry. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Orwin, for Richard Oliffe, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Crane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Probably a translation of: Discours veritable de la victoire obtenue par le roy en la bataille donnee pres le village d'Evry, le mercredy 14 iour de Mars, 1590.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The victorie obtained by the French King.</note>
                  <note>First and last leaves blank?.</note>
                  <note>See also STC 13113.5--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 13132.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20490:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:20490:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <p>A Diſcourſe and true recitall of euerie particular of the <hi>victorie obtained by the French</hi> King, on Wedneſday the fourth of March, being Aſhwedneſday.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo of his good ſucceſſe that he hath had</hi> ſince that time, in taking of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Townes.</p>
            <p>Out of French into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Seene and Allowed.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>BY WISDOME PEACE BY PEACE PLENTY</q>
               <p>T O</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Orwin</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>Thomas Orwin,</hi> for <hi>Richard Oliffe,</hi> and are <hi>to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Church-yard, at the</hi> Signe of the Crane. 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20490:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:20490:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <head>A Diſcourſe and true recitall of <hi>euerie particular of the victorie</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the King of <hi>France,</hi> on <hi>Wedneſday the</hi> 4. <hi>of March be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Aſhwedneſday.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV vnderſtood by my laſt aduertiſement how God had giuen victorie to the king o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his enemies: ſince which rime I haue endeuoured my ſelfe to learne the truth of all things, as neere as I could, of ſuch as were preſent at the fight, who ſay the victorie as it fell out, was a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous worke of God: for the forces of the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> were 4500. horſe, aſwell armed as poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, amongſt which were 1600. Launces, and the reſt Petronells armed, and 18000. footmen, and the forces of the King were 2000. horſe, and 12000. foote. The King was aduertiſed that the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> was paſſed the Riuer at <hi>Maunte,</hi> and that he iornied with great boldnes towards him: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it was aduiſed in counſell to raiſe his ſiege be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dreux,</hi> which had ſuſtained two aſſaults, and ſo vpon monday the 2. of March the King raiſed
<pb facs="tcp:20490:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->his ſiege, &amp; encamped himſelfe ſo neere the Duke, that the ſame night certaine Marſhalls of the Duke lodged in certaine Villages were diſlodged by the King, and there lodged himſelfe by force. The next morning the King did put himſelfe into the field in a faire plaine, and ſawe that the Duke was retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned betweene Saint <hi>Andre</hi> and <hi>Yury</hi> nere <hi>Annet,</hi> three quarters of a mile further than he was the day before, which troubled the King much to ſeeke him ſo farre; which was great aduantage to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, and perill to the King to approach them, which made them to leaue a Village that they held. This day was nothing performed but skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes. The Wedneſday morning the King cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed euerie man to bee put in aray, he himſelfe orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the whole, and gaue order that ſo ſoone as they heard one peece of Ordnance ſhot of, they ſhould prepare themſelues to the battaile.</p>
            <p>The Duke by his Eſpialls had diſcouered the ſigne of the Cannon, but vnderſtood it had been to haue prepared for their departure, and therefore ſought by all meanes to knowe which way the King ment to flee, and truſſed vp his baggage to followe: but it fell out otherwiſe, for at this ſigne euerie man was prepared.</p>
            <p>The Tueſday before, the Duke ſent to knowe how the King was apparelled, whereby to knowe him, the better to lay to kill him. The King being aduertiſed hereof, ſent a Tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet to tell him, that he was ſorie he took ſo much paine, &amp; that he would caſe him of that care, and that he gaue him to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand,
<pb facs="tcp:20490:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->that (if he had deſire to ſee him) he ſhould finde him mounted vpon a gray horſe, with a great white feather in his creſt armed in blew and black, and deſired to knowe how he would be armed and mounted, for that he deſired to ſpeake with him verie neere; vnto the which he anſwered, he would be armed in red, but the gallant was armed in black. The King hauing commaunded all into battaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray, did command euerie one to pray, which they all gladlie did in particular. This done, the king be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to march forward with ſome part of his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of horſe, and cauſed one of the ſquadrons of his horſe to approach behinde him, in the which was the Artillerie, which was ſhot with ſuch furie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Reiſters,</hi> thrice out of euerie Cannon, that he made at euery ſhot a faire breach: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they did not let to come to the charge, where they were well receiued; and of the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons which the enemie diſcharged, there was but one ſhot that hurt, wherewith was ſlaine of the Kings Cornet foure or fiue perſons. The Cornet of the King was ſo hardlie aſſailed by 1600. horſe in 4. parts, that he that bare the Cornet was throwne downe, &amp; all that troope forced to retire. The King which was in another Cornet than in his owne, hauing left <hi>Chiccot</hi> apparelled like himſelfe, ſauing he had two Foxe tailes hanging in his Helmet, was merueilouſly charged, thinking it had bin the king, for the which <hi>Chiccot</hi> did mock them, &amp; defended himſelfe valiantlie. The King ſeeing the ſaid Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ſo hardlie aſſailed, came to the head of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
<pb facs="tcp:20490:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->encouraging his Armie, which began to retire crying <hi>Amoy enfans,</hi> it is I that am the King, and his feather being high mounted, ſerued fora ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, and then euerie one began to returne to the King, and charged the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Wallons,</hi> which ſhewed themſelues valiant men: but if it had not been for the comming of the King, all his men had fled. Vpon which returne and charge, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Wallons</hi> ſodainlie began to flee, who were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie purſued by the King and his men, who gaue them no time, once being broken, to ioyne againe, charging them in ſundry places. The Marſhal <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> charged the <hi>Reiſters,</hi> and paſſed and repaſſed twiſe through them: wherevpon the faid <hi>Reiſters</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Wallons</hi> flee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which were 1600. Launces wel mounted; fled alſo. The Marſhal <hi>Daumont</hi> purſuing them, met the Launce Knights, who charged him, and cauſed him to ſtay to fight but the Launce Knights ſtood but a while, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into a ſmall Wood, whether the footmen of the King went to them, and put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al to the ſword.</p>
            <p>While this battaile was fighting, the Lord of <hi>Humieres</hi> of <hi>Picardie</hi> arriued with 300<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> horſe to the King, who charged alſo the <hi>Wallons,</hi> and came in good time. The King fearing at the firſt he and his companie had been enemies that had come to charge him: but when he ſawe them to aſſaile the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> hee reioyced and was glad, and then ſent to knowe what he was, and it was anſwered, that it was <hi>Humieres.</hi> This man helped the King much to ouerthrowe the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Wallons,</hi> who
<pb facs="tcp:20490:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->ſtood <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> valiantlie before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to ſaie trueth, there was none that fought well of the enemies ſide that day but they: By the opinion of thoſe that were at the battaile; that firſt without the helpe of God, and ſecondarelie, the valiantnes of the King, and thirdlie the happie comming of <hi>Humieres,</hi> the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile had been loſt on the Kings ſide. But marke a notable miracle, in a moment out men retired, in a moment againe returned, &amp; after in a moment put the enemies to ſlight: for ſo ſoone as the King had gathered againe his men together, ſetting vppon them, the feare of God ſtrooke them, (for by the iudgement of men, they had no other occaſion) and ſo fled: alſo it was thought they feared the Marſhall <hi>Byron,</hi> who all this while ſtood in a heape with 600. Horſe to ſuſtaine and giue helpe to the weakeſt parte of the Kings bartaile, but when the King ſent him word to giue helpe to his Cornet which was ſore oppreſſed, he made anſwere; that his lying ſtill did giue more terror &amp; feare to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie making ſigne euerie mynute to ſet vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than if he had entred the battaile, for if he had char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the enemie, they ſhould no longer haue feared, ſeeing all the Kings forces to bee imployed. There were three Cornets of the Kings, which at the firſt retired, of the which S. <hi>Bonet</hi> which bare the corner of Captain <hi>Rowlet</hi> vvas one. The ſaid <hi>Rowlet</hi> remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſtill in the Kings Camp onlie with 12. Laſices, but afterwards did put himſelfe into another Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net to fight <hi>Gerponuile</hi> who carried the Cornet of the Gouernour of <hi>Deepe</hi> fel vnder his horſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb facs="tcp:20490:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->one of the greateſt and ritcheſt Barons of <hi>Caux,</hi> being the commanders Lieftenant ran to the baggage to keepe it obtaining thereby great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. In briefe, there were many aſtonied, and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie had it not been thorough the great endeuour of the King who with Marſhall <hi>D'aumont</hi> and others hauing their hearts &amp; minds fullie bent, ſtil incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging his people all had been loſt. <hi>De Maine</hi> ſeeing this hard onſet, ſtayed not the charging of himſelfe although he had with him 500. horſe but betooke him to his ſpurres, by <hi>Deuery</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the riuer of <hi>Eury,</hi> which ſtoode by good hap for him. The Knight <hi>D'aumal</hi> and <hi>D'namures</hi> without fight ran awaie, then euerie one purſued the enemie by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the King. The footemen ſeeing the Tragedie, (that is to ſate) the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> and <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers,</hi> kept their place, &amp; holding downe their pikes cried for mercie. The King ſent to take away their Enſignes, and then took them to mercie: the Lance-Knights were all put to the ſworde for their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at <hi>Arkes. De Maine</hi> ran away by the bridge of <hi>Deuery,</hi> and caſt awaie his Caſſock and tooke a Mandilian of a Soldier, and paſsing through his owne men ſlew foure or fiue whereby more eaſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to paſſe, and cauſed a Barricado to bee made at the bridge and placed ſoldiers there to defende the purſuite, the King comming to the ſaid Barricado, and ſeeing ſome let beeing conducted by <hi>Chiccot,</hi> who aſſured him that hee knew the waie, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to paſſe by a ſhallowe, and purſued <hi>De Maine</hi> to the Suburbes of <hi>Maunte,</hi> which was 7. leagues
<pb facs="tcp:20490:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->from the place. The Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> was an houre at the gates intreating entrie, which at the firſt they denyed, telling him they feared leaſt the King ſhould enter with him in the purſuite, whereupon hee ſware hee had killed the King with his owne hands, but in trueth had loſt the battaile, by which meanes he entred, &amp; if he had ſtaied but one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an houre longer he had been diſpatched, and had it not bin for the Barricado at the bridge of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery,</hi> which letted them, and his ſpeedie departure from the battaile, he had been either ſlaine or taken. He ſaued himſelfe from thence to <hi>Pontois</hi> and ſo to Saint <hi>Denis:</hi> hee cauſed all the Peſants to riſe by the reporte of his men that were priſoners, to kill al them that ſhould flee: he commanded all the nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of <hi>France</hi> to be ſlaine without ſparing any: he ordered alſo meanes to kil the King, in which God hath changed his purpoſe. There were taken in the place of the battaile foure Cannons and other ſmall peeces, all his baggage, powder and munition, a great number of Charriots and horſes of the <hi>Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Germaines</hi> and <hi>Wallons:</hi> in briefe, the Peſants are by that meanes rich, a great number of the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were drowned. The Barricado of <hi>Deuery,</hi> was after taken by the Kings ſide, and many men ſlaine there. In the battaile were ſlaine not paſt 1500. but in the purſuite of the flight was the great ſlaughter. The confuſion was ſo great, that the baggage of <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conte</hi> were carried away by the enemie fleeing to <hi>Vernone,</hi> but afterwards were recouered. There were 60. Enſignes &amp; 40. Cornets
<pb facs="tcp:20490:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->taken, the white Cornet of <hi>de Maine,</hi> the King (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſlaine the bearer) tooke himſelfe. The King hath licenſed the <hi>Switzers</hi> to depart, and hath giuen them a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uoy to their Cantons, allowing them ſixe pence a day during their trauell home, with aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement that they ſhould come no more againſt the Crowne of <hi>France.</hi> There is 6000. footmen <hi>French,</hi> which haue ſworne ſeruice to the King, curſing <hi>de Maine</hi> that he left them to the butcherie of the Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, praiſing greatlie the King for his great mercie. The King as yet will not accept of their feruice. The Countie <hi>Egmond</hi> was ſlaine there by the hands of Marſhal <hi>Daumont,</hi> who was Colonell of the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> cannot bee found, but is thought to be dead: <hi>Founrden Martell</hi> dead, <hi>Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonpierre, Chattenneraies, Baddolphen,</hi> &amp; diuers others dead in the place. There is of the <hi>Wallons</hi> paſt at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miens</hi> 350. or 400. whereof 120. left in the Hoſpital being hurt. <hi>De Maine</hi> did ſend after them to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miens</hi> to come to him by the <hi>Signeur Belleangliſe:</hi> to whom they anſwered, they would not returne, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>de Maine</hi> Runne-away. The King commanded all the ſtrangers to be ſlaine, and the <hi>French</hi> to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. There are few <hi>Spaniards</hi> or <hi>Italians</hi> left aliue, except thoſe which ſaued themſelues by flight<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for although they offered great ſommes of money for their ranſume, yet were they all ſlaine. The Peſants mocked <hi>de Maine,</hi> ſaying he cauſed them to come to kill the Kings men, but yet killed the others, and cryed, <hi>God ſaue the King.</hi> It is the moſt norable vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie that of late was heard of, and being throughly
<pb facs="tcp:20490:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->conſidered, muſt be confeſſed to come of God.</p>
            <p>The Tueſday night before the battaile, there was ſeene in this place two Armies in the Skie, the one greater than the other, and the leſſe ouercame the greater. This ſight was ſeene at the time of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of the Battaile; &amp; the like at the ſame time in the Camp; &amp; now we vnderſtand the iſſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the victorie. God hath ſhewed himſelfe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantlie to fauour the cauſe, in ſo much that they ſay in the Campe, that the praiers of the Hugonots are much auaileable in the ſight of God. <hi>Vernone</hi> yeelded on Friday after, and the King entred it on Saterday: <hi>Maurte</hi> yeelded vpon Monday, and the King entred it vpon Tueſday. There was found 3. great Cannons with powder and ſhot, and there the King refreſhed himſelfe well. The 28. day the King departed out of <hi>Maunte</hi> to go to <hi>Corbell, Mens</hi> &amp; <hi>Mullen,</hi> where the Duke of <hi>Longueuile</hi> hath 2500. horſe, and 6000. footmen: which Townes are like to bee deliuered to the King, the which will bee a great helpe to aduance the parlie of them of <hi>Paris,</hi> which they ſeeke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monſieur de Villeroy</hi> hath bin at <hi>Maunte,</hi> &amp; hath ſince twiſe ſpoken with the Marſhall <hi>Byron.</hi> The King hath licenſed the Gentlemen of baſe <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> to goe home to their houſes to refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, hauing ſufficient forces beſides. <hi>Monſieur de Tauannes</hi> fleeing from the Battell, hath retired him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to <hi>Roan,</hi> in ſhewe, to keepe them aſſured to <hi>de Maine. Monſieur de Villiers</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Newha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20490:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->comming thether, being called by the Countrie to take the gouernment and ſtrong places, hath bin repulſed by <hi>Monſieur de Tauannes</hi> and <hi>Milray.</hi> And although they make great ſhewe to withſtand the King, yet haue they reſolued in their priuate coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to yeeld, the King comming by force, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting any reſcue at all.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>de Aumale</hi> is in <hi>Picardie,</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> hath withdrawne him, his wife and children out of <hi>Paris,</hi> and conueied his wife and children to <hi>Perone.</hi> Himſelfe is now at <hi>Soiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> gathering what forces he can; but not likelie to gather any at this preſent, hauing no other hope, but the accuſtomed lyes of his preachers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his wonted practizes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Deepe</hi> 
                  <date>the 20. of March. 1590.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20490:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
